好了  给你
Okay, okay. Here you go.
我们再来一遍
And let's go again.
这只是几号  九号吗
Which one is this? Number nine?
是的  是九号
Yeah, this is number nine.
我们叫她明眸
Bright Eyes, we call her.
你看到了吗
Are you watching this?
太不可思议了
This is unbelievable.
我的天啊
Oh, my God.
她用了几步  二十步
How many moves was that? 20.
满分是十五步
Yeah, a perfect score is 15.
博士  你给她用了什么药
Doc, what are you giving her?
把那录像给我
Hey, give me that video!
九号猩猩  就用了一剂药
Chimp number nine, just one dose.
不是应该过会儿见你吗
Aren't I seeing you later?
我们万事俱备了
We are good to go.
一会儿打给你  好的  再见
I'm going to call you back. Yeah, all right. Thanks. Bye.
112号药奏效了
The 112. It works.
只在一只猩猩上用过
On just the one primate.
一只足够了
One is all we need.
这药能全面恢复认知力
Full cognitive recovery.
我们准备好了
We're ready.
你确定没有操之过急吗
Look, are you sure you're not rushing this?
我进行此项研究已经有五年半了
I've been working on this for five and a half years.
研究数据无懈可击
The data is clear.
斯蒂芬  我们准备好了
We're ready, Steven.
只等你批准进行人体试验了
All I need is your approval for human trials.
人体试验需要董事会的批准
For this, you're going to need the board's approval.
威尔  这研究可是花了大血本的
There's a lot of money riding on this, Will.
你只有一次机会
You only get one shot.
一次机会足矣
One shot is all I need.
好的  但是我要看
All right. But I'll need to see
所有的研究报告  没问题
all the research. You got it.
威尔  什么事
And, Will... Yeah?
别太感情用事
Keep your personal emotions out of it.
那帮投资人看重的是成果  不是你的梦想
These people invest in results, not dreams.
好的
Okay.
来见见九号猩猩
Meet chimp nine.
视频中她正在玩汉诺塔
Here she is tasking at what is called the Lucas Tower,
游戏的目标是
the object of which
通过在三根柱子间调整每层塔的位置
is to move the tower from peg to peg,
使塔层从大到小排列
without placing a larger block
游戏中大片不能压在小片上面
on top of a smaller block.
不出所料  她根本无法完成游戏
As expected, she was unable to complete the puzzle at all.
之后  我们给她用了叫ALZ112的药
Then, we gave her what we call ALZ-112,
这是一种基因疗法
a gene therapy
促使大脑产生出新的脑细胞
that allows the brain to create its own cells
来完成自我修复
in order to repair itself.
在生物学上  这叫新生神经元
In biology, this is called neurogenesis.
在基因系统公司
Here at Gen-Sys,
我们将之视为治疗老年痴呆症的特效药
we call it the cure to Alzheimer's.
唐尼  你让她准备好了吗
Donnie, you get her ready?
她怯场了
She's got stage fright.
是吗
Is that what it is?
她要把我的手弄断了
She is going to break my hand!
放手  明眸  放手
Let go. Bright Eyes, let go!
你没事吧
Are you all right?
我们已准备好进入下个阶段  人体试验
We're ready to move on to the next phase. Human trials.
给你  明眸
Here you go, Bright Eyes.
这是你最喜欢的汽水  来吧
It's your favorite fizzy soda, come on.
开始吧  唐尼
Let's go, Donnie.
这回应该可以把她带下楼了
We should have her downstairs already.
乖孩子
Okay? Good girl.
出来吧  没事
Come on out, girl. That's right.
这是给你的
That's for you.
唐尼  套她脖子  套脖子
Around the neck, Donnie! Around the neck.
套脖子啊  天哪
Around the neck! Jesus!
唐尼  快套住她  开门啊
Donnie, do it now! Open up!
唐尼
Donnie!
我来麻醉她
I'm going to sedate her.
不  门  快去关门
No, no, no, no! Door! Get the door!
不  不  不
No, no, no, no.
全面封锁  全面封锁
Close it down. Close it down now!
去找人帮忙  唐尼  站起来
Go get help. Donnie! Donnie! Come on.
使用112号药尚未出现任何副作用
There have been absolutely no side effects associated with 112.
除了一点
With one exception.
出于某种原因
For some reason,
猩猩的虹膜上出现了绿色的斑点
the chimps' irises exhibit flecks of green.
其实  九号猩猩是首次发现这个现象
Actually, we first noticed it in chimp nine.
所以我们才叫她明眸
Hence her nickname, Bright Eyes.
一会儿把她带来后你们就能看到
You will see when we bring her in.
小心
Watch out!
理论上
In theory,
这个疗法能用来
this therapy can be used
治疗许多种类的大脑疾病
to treat a wide range of brain disorders.
它的用途无可限量
It is virtually limitless.
所带来的经济利益也是无可限量的
As are the potential profits, which is why
因此我们相信你们会同意进行人体试验
we are confident that you will vote to approve human trials.
不要  不要
No! No!
雅各布先生  求你了
Mr. Jacobs? Mr. Jacobs, I am begging you.
求你别这么做
I am begging you not to do this.
花钱在实验室
Look, it would cost a small fortune to run lab work-ups
研究这些猩猩
on all of those chimps
最后也不过是我所见到的这样
only to tell me what I already know.
这些猩猩都被感染了
That they are contaminated.
他们对实验室至关重要啊
There are lives at stake here.
这些动物是有个性有感情的
These are animals with personalities, with attachments.
有感情  是的
Attachments? Yeah.
我经营的是公司  不是宠物园
I run a business, not a petting zoo.
找个最经济的办法把这些猩猩处理掉
Find the most cost-effective way to put those apes down.
我做不到
I can't do that.
你是猩猩管理员  搞定这件事
You're the chimp handler. Handle it.
斯蒂芬
Steven?
刚才真是开心一刻啊
Well, that was fun.
他们拿走了112号药
They've taken the 112.
董事会拒绝了你的申请
The board have rejected your proposal.
他们准备让其他项目上马
They've chosen to advance other programs.
你多少总能做点什么的吧
Well, there must be something that you can do.
是的  我可以炒了你
Yes, there is. I could fire you.
我没开玩笑  董事会和我讨论过
Believe me, we talked about it.
我们有五年的完整数据
We have five years of conclusive data.
尽管炫耀你的数据吧
Parade all the data you want,
没人会再投一分钱给你的项目了
you will never convince anyone to invest another dime.
这药能救人性命
This drug has the potential to save lives.
我看更有可能让公司倒闭
To bankrupt this company, more like.
天啊  你对人脑如此了解
I swear, you know everything about the human brain
却唯独不懂它的运作方式
except the way it works.
你从头开始开发112号药吧
Go back to the drawing board on the 112.
从分子开发开始
Start again in molecular development.
想办法比其他人早一步完成研究
Find a way to get there before someone else does.
还有  去收拾下这烂摊子
And clean up this mess.
富兰克林
Franklin?
猩猩生了只小猩猩
They carry small.
她被送来的时候肯定已经怀孕了
She must have been pregnant when they brought her in.
所以就因为这个
So that's why...
明眸
她表现出的不是侵略性  而是保护的本能
She wasn't being aggressive, she was just being protective?
明眸
她表现出的不是侵略性  而是保护的本能
She wasn't being aggressive, she was just being protective?
她以为我们要伤害她的孩子
She thought we were going to hurt her baby.
来抱抱
Come here.
我想自己养它  但我姐夫是这里的保安
I'd take him myself, but my brother-in-law works for security.
他肯定会告发我的
He'd rat me out in a second.
什么  你要我把它带回去吗
What, you want me to take it home?
我不懂怎么照顾猴子
I can't take care of a monkey.
他不是猴子  是猩猩
He's not a monkey, he's an ape.
富兰克林  我
Franklin, I...
就几天
It's just for a couple days,
等我给他找个安身之所  拜托了
until I find a sanctuary. That's all I need.
富兰克林  不行  他不是我的责任
Franklin, no. Look, this isn't my responsibility.
他是公司的财产
This is company property.
好  我这么跟你说吧  博士
Okay. I'm going to tell you what, Doc.
雅各布让我解决其他十二只
Jacobs made me put down the other 12.
我受够了
I'm done.
你请自便吧
Be my guest.
你好  你好
Hey. Hi.
你好像很累啊  是的
Oh, you look beat. Yeah.
他怎么样
How is he doing?
他时好时坏
Well, he has good days and bad days.
今天不怎么在状态
Today, not so good.
虽然他一直在引用莎士比亚的作品
Although, he has been quoting Shakespeare.
你养了只宠物啊
Oh, you got a pet.
就临时养养
Just a temporary house guest.
养只宠物可能对他有帮助
Oh. Well, it might be good for him.
是的  晚安
Yeah. Good night.
授予
荣誉证书  最受喜爱的音乐教师
查尔斯·罗德曼先生
你好  老爸
Hey, Dad.
老爸  威尔
Dad? Will!
我没听见你进屋
Hi. I didn't hear you come in.
今天是个大日子  对吧
Today is the day, right?
你以为我忘了
You thought I'd forget.
今天你有个重要的考试对吧  是化学吗
You have a big test today, right? Chemistry?
老爸  有东西给你看
Hey, Dad, do you want to see something?
什么
What?
这是什么  他受伤了吗
What is that? Is he injured?
没有  那是个胎记吧
No, I think that is a birthmark.
"但是对于凯撒
"But as for Caesar,
出自莎士比亚《安东尼与克莉奥佩屈拉》
他却跪下去  跪下去  惊服赞叹"
Kneel down, kneel down, and wonder."
别太投入了
Yeah, don't get too attached.
他真太可爱了  是吗
He is a cute little guy, isn't he?
我的车钥匙呢
Where are my car keys?
我的车钥匙  你放哪里了  老爸
My car keys! Where did you put them? Dad.
你现在不开车了
You don't drive anymore.
我知道
I know that.
给你
Here,
你来喂他吧
why don't you feed him?
你行吗  当然可以
Can you do that? Of course I can.
威尔  快来看
Will, look at this.
他出生才多久  一两天吧
How old is he? A day old? Two days old?
他真聪明  不是吗
Well, he is a smart one, isn't he?
你准备给他起什么名字
What are you going to name him?
还不知道
I don't know.
三年后
自出生起
Right away,
三年后
凯撒就显示出了高智慧的迹象
Caesar displayed signs of heightened intelligence.
所以我留下了他并在家里进行研究工作
So I kept him and brought my work home.
他十八个月时
By 18 months,
已会二十四个单词的手语了
Caesar was signing up to 24 words.
他两岁时
By age two,
就能完成为八岁以上小孩
Caesar was completing puzzles and models
设计的模型游戏
designed for children eight years and up.
他三岁时
At age three,
所显示出的认知能力
Caesar continues to show cognitive skills
远远超过与他同龄的人类小孩
that far exceed that of a human counterpart.
家  家
Home. Home.
他用十五步完成了汉诺塔
He completed the Lucas Tower in fifteen moves,
满分
a perfect score.
我坚持我的假设
I maintain my hypothesis
首先  他眼球上的绿色斑点
that, A, the green in his eyes
说明ALZ112的药效
indicates that the ALZ-112
通过母婴遗传传给了他
was passed genetically from mother to son
其次  由于没有需要修复的受损脑细胞
and, B, that in the absence of damaged cells that need replacing,
他体内的药物
the drug in his system has
大幅提升了健康大脑的机能
radically boosted healthy brain functioning.
而且
And,
他象棋下得极好
he plays chess pretty well.
这是我的台灯  是我的房间
It's my lamp! And my room!
老爸
Dad?
这儿不需要你
I don't need you here.
伊琳娜  对不住了
lrena, l'm sorry.
这活儿没法干了
I can't do this anymore.
应该送他去老人院
He belongs in a home.
他没办法这样继续生活了
This is no way for him to live.
是的  没法活了
Yeah, and no way to live.
没法活了
No way to live.
这是我的台灯  我一直
Now, it's my lamp. I'm always...
ALZ112
老爸  这药会让你好起来的
It'll make you better, Dad.
老爸
Dad?
多得  进屋来吃早饭了
Todd! Come inside for breakfast!
我要记下从实验室拿的药品
I'll need to keep track of what I take from the lab.
尽管如此  我想
Although, I don't foresee
你一个月用一支完全够了
you needing more than one treatment a month.
奇迹发生了  是啊
Something amazing has happened. Yeah.
我要给你验个血做个扫描
I'll need a blood test,
再分析下用药的剂量
and a scan and the dosage.
必须对你进行仔细的观察  威尔
You'll have to be carefully monitored. Will...
如果我能带些
Now if I can sneak some...
威尔  干嘛
Will! Yeah?
我的病好了
I'm not sick anymore.
愿意效劳
It was nothing, Dad.
凯撒  他去哪里了  我要看看他
Caesar. Where's Caesar? I want to see him.
凯撒
Caesar?
Caesar!
他应该不会跑远的
All right, he can't have gone far.
凯撒
Caesar!
爸爸  爸爸
Daddy? Daddy!
凯撒
Caesar!
滚出去  滚
Get out of here! Get out!
滚出去
Get out! Get out of here!
住手  够了
Hey, hey, hey! Enough! Enough!
你他妈怎么回事啊
The hell is the matter with you?
如果那畜生再靠近我家或是我的孩子
If I see that animal anywhere near my house or my kids again...
他没有威胁的
He's not dangerous.
不会有下次了  最好别有
It won't happen again. Damn right, it won't.
走吧  老爸
Come on, Dad.
他只是想玩玩
He just wanted to play.
待家里  老爸处理好了
Stay in the house. Daddy's got it.
告诉过你别一个人出门
I told you not to go out without us.
天啊  没事了
Oh, God. It's okay.
严重吗
How bad is it?
我不知道
I don't know.
他喜欢你
He likes you.
别担心
Don't worry.
很快就弄好了  之后给你买好吃的
It'll be over soon and we can go get a treat.
冰激凌怎么样
I'm thinking ice cream.
好主意
Good idea.
你教会他用手语了
You taught him to sign?
就些简单的词
Just a handful of things.
都是些最基本的
Basic stuff.
他在说什么
What's he saying?
没什么
Nothing.
你看我们什么时候来复诊
So, when do you think we should come back?
你们不需要复诊
Well, you won't need to
缝合的线是可溶性的
come back because the stitches are dissolvable.
就是要注意有没有感染
I would just say watch out for signs of infection.
发热  红肿什么的
Fever, redness.
好吧  这次他在说什么
Okay. What's he saying now?
他说你和我应该一起吃顿饭
Well, he thinks that you and I should have dinner together.
很怪是吧
I know.
凯撒  走吧
Hey, Caesar. Come on.
卡罗琳  很高兴再见到你
Good to see you again, Caroline.
凯撒  你来吗
You coming, Caesar?
你教他的秘诀是什么
So, what's your secret?
不是我的功劳  是他遗传得好
I can't take any credit. It's in his genes.
你太谦虚了  他真的太棒了
I think you're being very modest. He's pretty amazing.
你在这儿给凯撒营造了个很温馨的家
I think you've built a pretty good home for Caesar here.
但是
But?
他不会一直这么点大
He won't stay this way for long.
他很快就会长成又大又壮的
He's gonna soon grow into a large, powerful animal.
过来
Come here.
他最近好吗
How has he been doing?
我想还不错
Okay. I think.
我喜欢猩猩  但是我也害怕他们
I love chimpanzees. I'm also afraid of them.
有这种畏惧之情很正常
And it's appropriate to be afraid of them.
凯撒不会伤害别人的
Caesar would never hurt anyone.
他在这儿很开心
He's happy here. Come on.
是的  看得出
Yeah, I can see that.
我们至少该给他些室外活动吧
Can we at least give him some open space?
没错  这是个好主意
Yeah. That probably would be a good idea.
我知道个地方  过了桥就到
I know a place right across the bridge.
红树林  那儿美极了
The redwoods. It's paradise.
来吧  来吧
Come on. Come on.
过来
Come here.
不用给他套绳索  他没问题的  走吧
He doesn't need a leash. He'll be fine. Come on.
安全起见  走吧
Just to be safe. Come on.
来吧  凯撒
Come on, Caesar.
这儿就是红树林
This is the redwoods.
凯撒  听着
Caesar? All right.
如果我把项圈解下来  你可不能跑远啊
If I take this off, you cannot leave my sight.
你跑远了我就找不到你了  好吗
I would never find you again. Okay.
这是什么意思  他在干什么
What is this? What's he doing?
真不敢相信
I don't believe that.
怎么了  他在请求你的允许
What? He's asking your permission.
这是恳求的手势
It's a supplicating gesture.
没事
It's okay.
去吧  凯撒  去玩吧
Come on, Caesar. Off you go!
去看着他
Look at him go.
凯撒  凯撒
Caesar! Caesar!
凯撒
Caesar!
你在这
There you are.
凯撒
Caesar?
去吧  凯撒  爬上去
Go on, Caesar. Climb!
爬高点
Go higher.
爬吧
Climb!
小心点
Just be careful.
凯撒  小心
Caesar, be careful!
五年后
你好啊
Hi.
怎么样  老兄
What's going on, buddy?
也给你分点爱
You get some love, too.
快点  亲爱的
Come on, honey.
那不是一头黑猩猩吗
Is that a chimpanzee?
你好
Hi.
停下
Come on!
快走
Come on.
凯撒  凯撒
Caesar? Caesar.
快走
Come on.
没事了  快走吧
It's all right. Come on.
好了  来吧
All right, come on.
我们走  你不上车吗
Let's go. You getting in?
凯撒
Caesar?
你还好吗  老弟
You okay, pal?
你是宠物吗  不
Are you a pet? No.
你不是宠物
You're not a pet.
我是你爸爸
I'm your father.
凯撒从哪里来
What is Caesar?
好吧
Okay.
凯撒  这是我工作的地方
Caesar, this is where I work.
也是你出生的地方
This is where you were born.
你妈妈曾经和其他黑猩猩住在这里
Your mother was here with other chimpanzees.
但是她现在已经不在了
But she's not here anymore.
所以
So,
我才把你带回家跟我一起住
that's why I took you home to live with me.
对
Yeah.
你妈妈去世了
Your mother is dead.
事实是  她被注射了药物
The thing is, she was given medicine.
和我给查尔斯用的是同一种药
Like the medicine I give to Charles.
她把药物影响遗传给了你
She passed it on to you.
所以你才这么聪明
That's why you're so smart.
我们带他回家吧
Let's take him home.
好的
Okay.
过来  给我解释解释
Come on, explain it to me.
好吧
All right.
我为了救他把他偷偷带出实验室
I snuck him out of the lab to save his life.
那个时候我根本不知道
I had no idea that the effects
药物影响已经从他妈妈那直接遗传给他了
had been transferred vertically from his mother.
但自那个时候起
But since then, he's been
他就显示出惊人的高智力水平
displaying incredible signs of intelligence.
我设计药物112是为了治病
I designed the 112 for repair,
但凯撒所表现出的已经远超我的初衷
but Caesar has gone way beyond that.
这是他去年的智商
Here is his lQ from last year.
从那时起到现在  他的智商已经翻倍
Since then, it's doubled.
这样不对  威尔
This is wrong, Will.
我的父亲曾经病入膏肓
My father was gone.
这种药治好了他
This drug brought him back.
你从没见过他重病的样子
You never saw how bad he was.
他重获新生了  那凯撒怎么办
He has his life again. And what about Caesar?
他怎么了  他怎么生活
What about him? Where does he fit in?
跟我过
With me.
跟我们过
With us.
听着
Listen,
我知道对你来说很难
I know it's been hard for you,
但是你在试图控制
but you're trying to control
本不应该受控的东西
things that are not meant to be controlled.
112号药起作用了
The 112 works.
你意识到你在说什么吗
Do you realize how you sound?
我只是想说  这是件好事
All I'm saying is, this is a good thing.
凯撒就是证据  我父亲也是
Caesar is proof of that. So is my father.
凯撒  吃饭
Caesar, eat your food.
爸爸  你还好吗
Dad, are you okay?
我很好
Yeah, I'm fine.
抗体
Antibodies.
他的机能对112号药产生了抗体
His system has found a way to fight the 112 virus
所以药物无法发挥疗效了
so that it can't deliver its therapy.
我父亲比以前病的更重了
My father's disease is going to return with a vengeance.
宝贝  你看见车蜡了吗
Honey, have you seen the car wax?
是台福特野马
It's a Mustang.
看起来美极了  我做了什么
It's looking great. What did I do...
停下
Stop!
你现在就给我停下
You stop right now!
给我出来  从车里出来
Get out of there! Get out of that car!
你他妈在干什么  从我车里滚出来
What the hell are you doing? Get out of my car!
我说了  给我滚出来
I said get out of my car!
我是个飞行员  我还得去机场呢
I'm a pilot! I got to get to the airport!
我现在怎么去机场
How am I going to get there now, huh?
你他妈给我个回答  你犯什么病了
Answer the goddamned question! What were you doing?
我也有辆车
I have a car just...
这不明摆着
Well, it's not obviously...
我听够了  让警察来处理
That's it, I'm done. The police can handle this.
你给我老实待着  你哪都不许去
You stay right there! You are going nowhere, mister!
你或是你儿子得给我赔偿损失
You or your son are going to pay for this!
反正我一个子儿不出
But I sure as hell am not going to!
这是你的问题  你把我车撞坏了
This is your problem! You made the mess!
我受够你们爷俩了  我这就
I'm sick of the two of you! I'm not going...
你给我待着别动
You stay right there!
不
No!
不要  不要
No! No!
凯撒  住手
Caesar! Stop!
爸爸
Daddy!
不  不
No, no.
凯撒
Caesar!
好了
It's okay.
没事了  你不是故意的
It's okay. You didn't mean it.
没事了
It's okay.
动物管制
把那东西从他身上拿下来
Hey. Take that thing off of him.
你能不能把那东西拿掉  拜托
Will you take that thing off of him? Come on.
这样  我带他进去  行吗
Look. I'll take him in, okay?
不行  按照法院的命令  你不能
No, he's under court orders. You can't do that.
没关系  让他来吧
It's fine, let him.
准备好了就带他进来吧
Bring him in when you're ready.
拿掉它  谢谢你
Take it off. Thank you.
凯撒  凯撒  凯撒  凯撒  凯撒
Caesar, Caesar, Caesar, Caesar? Caesar.
现在不能回家  会没事的
Not right now. It's gonna be okay.
我们去看看里面什么样  好吗
Let's just see what it's like inside, okay?
来吧  凯撒  我们走
Come on, Caesar. Let's go.
来吧  相信我
Come on. Trust me.
还不错
It's okay.
去吧
Go on.
他从来没跟其他猩猩一起生活过
He hasn't spent any time with other chimps.
我们常处理这种情况
We're used to that.
一开始他会有一点焦躁
He'll be a little skittish at first,
不过我们会帮他融入进去的
but we'll integrate him.
你会惊讶于他们的适应能力
You'd be surprised how quick they adapt.
我们提供了一个很刺激的环境
We provide a stimulating environment.
他在这会茁壮成长
He's going to thrive here.
来吧  我们还得签几份文件
Come on, let's do some paperwork.
对了  进来的时候别忘了锁门
Oh, and make sure you lock that door when you come in.
凯撒
Caesar.
你会没事的
It's gonna be okay.
一切都会好起来
Everything is gonna be okay.
别害怕
Don't be scared.
你现在就暂住在这
You're gonna stay here now.
不行
No.
我们现在不能回家
We're not going home right now.
没事的
It's okay.
经验之谈  告别拖得越长
In our experience, the longer you drag out the goodbyes,
分手就越艰难
the harder it is.
我等一下再签好吗
Can I just sign that later?
十有八九他想你赶不上你想他多
You'll probably miss him more than he'll miss you.
给他几个星期让他适应这个地方就好了
Best give him a couple of weeks to get used to the place.
威尔  我们得走了
Will, we have to go.
我们得回家了
We have to go home.
我很快回来看你  好吗
I'm coming back soon, okay?
来之前打个电话就行
Just call ahead before you do.
过来
Hey, over here!
我能把你弄出去
Hey, I can get you out!
快来  过来
Come on. Over here.
快来  到下面来
Come on. Hey. Down here.
蠢猴子
Stupid monkey.
你就这点本事吗  放马过来吧
Is that all you got? Come on!
这就是一疯人院
It's a madhouse!
疯人院
法院还没定案  所以系统中查不到
Court order hasn't been filed, so it's not in the system.
归档之后
Once it comes through,
您将在九十天之内获知上诉日期
it'll take about 90 days before you receive an appeal date.
九十天  是的  先生  九十天
90 days? Yes, sir, 90 days.
我们会以邮件形式通知您  等等
You'll be notified by mail. Hang on.
我来告诉你应该怎么做
Right. Here's what's gonna happen.
你坐回电脑旁
You're going to go back on your computer,
给我调整一下日程
you're gonna shift things around,
在这个星期安排一个
and you're going to get me
上诉日给我  懂了吗
a date for my appeal this week. You got it?
我帮不了您
I can't help you.
这么说我们要有麻烦了
All right, then we have a problem.
你要是不给我弄到我就不走了
Because l'm not moving until you do.
九十天  先生
90 days, sir.
能给你个上诉日你就该很感激了
Be thankful you're talking about court dates.
他们没打死那头畜生已经算你走运了
You're lucky they didn't put that animal down.
我一定尽快把他带回家  爸爸
I promise to get him back soon, Dad.
爸爸
Dad?
我父亲的免疫系统继续排斥112号药物
My father's immune system continues to reject the 112 virus,
基因治疗逐渐失效
rendering the gene therapy obsolete.
他的健康状况日渐恶化
His health is deteriorating,
而且病情也越发凶猛
and the disease is progressing rapidly.
我需要一种更强效的病毒品种
I need a more aggressive virus strain.
一种更快速的传导机制
A faster delivery method.
因为在这样的恶化速度之下
Because at this rate...
我不能失去他们两个
I can't lose them both.
我不会失去他们两个的
I won't lose them both.
我们能谈谈吗
Hi. Can we talk?
长话短说  我还有个会
Make it fast. I've got a meeting.
你经管基因系统公司十年了
In the 10 years you've been running Gen-Sys,
你推出过几种一下生产线
how many drugs have come down the pipeline
就能拯救千万生命
that could save millions of lives,
就能改变世界的药品呢
that could change everything?
你在说什么呢
What are you talking about?
ALZ112
The ALZ-112.
你怎么回事  威尔
What happened to you, Will?
你曾经是这个实验室的明星
You used to be the star of this lab.
但现在你都不怎么露面  就算露面
Now you hardly ever show, and when you do,
你也是把你和整个团队的时间
you waste your time and
浪费在钻研一种
that of your team's fixating on a drug that,
在经历那件事之后永远不会获批的药物上
after what happened, is never, ever going to get approved.
112号药是危险品  威尔
The 112 is dangerous, Will,
而且它没有效
and it doesn't work.
我在我爸爸身上试验了  它有效
I treated my father with it. It does work.
你干了什么  你干了什么
You did what? You did what?
他战胜了病魔  跟我们预测的一样
He beat the disease. Like we predicted.
把他带来  但是有一个并发症
Bring him in. There's been a complication.
那它到底有没有效呢
Well, does it work, or doesn't it?
我父亲的病最终复发了
My father's disease eventually outran the cure.
天哪
For goodness sake.
他的免疫系统对病毒产生了抗体
His immune system produced antibodies that beat the viral component,
但是它会有效的
but it will work.
我已经研发出一个病种
I've already developed a virus
我认为会更有效
strain that I think will be more aggressive.
你认为
You think?
只要让我开始试验
Just let me test it.
你是在浪费我的时间
You're wasting my time.
还有
There's more.
这种药物的作用已经不止于治病
The applications go beyond the disease.
有迹象表明
There are indications that show
该疗法能改善认知机能和记忆质量
that therapy can improve cognitive functioning, memory quality...
你说什么
What are you saying?
我的父亲不仅痊愈了  他还进步了
My father didn't just recover. He improved.
你是说智力增长吗
You mean increased intelligence?
还不很肯定  但是没错
It's not conclusive, but yes.
我要你尽快在黑猩猩上
I want you to start testing
试验改进后的112号药
the revised 112 on chimps ASAP.
好的  我会全力支持你
Okay. I'll give you whatever you need.
绝对的
Absolutely.
吃晚饭了
Dinner time!
A级灵长类专用炒饭
Grade A primate chow.
吃吧
Go on.
看见食物也不认识了吗
Don't you know food when you see it?
你觉得挺好玩是吧
You think that's funny, huh?
我给你看点好玩的
I'll show you something funny.
他马上就知道谁是老大了
He'll learn who's boss soon enough.
他的衣服怎么办  衣服怎么了
What about his clothes? What about them?
我也不知道
I don't know.
其他猿猴看见了可能不太高兴
It might cause problems with the other apes.
再好不过
Good.
基因系统公司
我数过了  十只猩猩  对吗
I've counted 10 apes. Correct?
对
Yep.
很好  一直推到最后面
Good. All the way to the back.
好的
Okay.
你们这个项目动作够快的  着什么急
You guys are moving really quick on this. What's the big rush?
回来第一天  你还是在抱怨
First day back, and you're still complaining.
库巴  你好  我是威尔
Koba. Hi, I'm Will.
就这只
Okay. This one.
他非常镇定
He's very calm.
是啊  这家伙可没少见识实验室
Yeah, this guy has seen the inside of a whole lot of labs.
程序他都知道
He knows the drill.
我能加入吗
Thought I'd join you.
看看进度
Watch our progress.
帮他准备好
Get him prepped.
戴好你的面具
Tighten your masks.
把113号药递给我
Pass me the 113.
脉搏正常  血压稳定
Pulse-ox is good, blood pressure steady.
雾化给药系统就位
Aerosol delivery in place.
释放113号药物
Releasing the 113.
富兰克林  把你面具戴上
Franklin, get your mask on!
好了吗  好了
Got it? Yeah.
把带子系紧
Tighten the straps.
你没事吧
You okay?
没事
Yeah, okay.
动起来  快走
Move it! Let's go!
起来锻炼去  你们这群懒狒狒
Get up and exercise, you lazy baboons!
雅各布斯
智力增长非常显著  无副作用
Intelligence results are remarkable. No adverse effects.
猩猩的免疫系统非常强大
Apes have amazingly strong immune systems.
对  没错  注意一下这一点
Yeah. All right, keep an eye on it.
好的
Okay.
对不起
Sorry about that.
这帮家伙比我恢复的好多了
These guys are more resilient than I am.
失陪一下
Excuse me a sec.
伤得重吗
Hurt bad?
你懂手语吗
You know sign?
马戏团正宗红毛大猩猩
Circus Orangutan.
这只可以了
He's good.
小心  人类不喜欢太聪明的猩猩
Careful. Human no like smart Ape.
基因系统公司
今晚活多  你要加班
I want you working late tonight.
基因系统公司还要三只
Gen-Sys needs three more of them.
你好  凯撒
Hey, Caesar. Hi.
你受伤了吗
Are you hurt?
我看看
Show me.
凯撒  手伸过来
Caesar. Give me your hand.
手伸过来我看看  没事的
Give me your hand. It's okay.
有时新人会挨整
Sometimes the new kid on the block gets picked on.
别担心  天哪  它们都干了些什么
Don't worry. God, what have they done to you?
你放屁  你怎么他了
That's bullshit. What the hell did you do?
算了  哥们  嘿  出什么事了
Let go, man. Hey! What's the problem here?
我现在就要带他出去
I'm taking him out of here. Right now.
没有法院的指令  休想
Not without a court order, you're not.
他不再属于你了
He's not yours anymore.
听好了  如果我发现他有一丁点遭虐待
I promise, if I find out he's been mistreated in any way,
我一定关了这地方
I'll have this place shut down.
你继续
Go on.
不是
No.
不行  你还不能马上回家
No, we're not going home right now.
我一定会带你出去的  我发誓
But I'm going to get you out of here. I promise.
相信我
You have to trust me.
凯撒  相信我  好吗
Caesar, you have to trust me. Okay?
探视时间到
I think this visit is over.
相信我  会好起来的
Trust me. It'll be okay.
快点  动起来  过来
Come on! Move it! Let's go!
有一百多只呢
Wow! There's hundreds of them.
简直是你的私人动物园
This is like your own private zoo.
更像是多毛家伙们的监狱
More like a prison for hairy dudes.
它们还有电视看啊
They watch TV?
我们称之为丰富生活
We call it enrichment.
这一只好可爱哦
This one's so cute!
他叫什么
What's his name?
叫康奈利娅  是母的
The name is Cornelia. It's a she.
哦天哪  别靠得太近
Oh, my God! Don't get too close.
这一只差点吓死我
This one scared me half to death.
那个大家伙叫毛利斯
Yeah. That big guy's called Maurice.
没意思
No fun.
过来  我给你看点有意思的
Here, I'll show you something fun.
看好了
Check this out.
你疯了吗
Are you insane?
你们不该进来
You shouldn't be in here.
下一个就电你
Hey, you're next!
好了  我们走吧
Come on, let's go.
这儿我都呆腻了
I spend too much time in here as it is.
走吧
Come on.
看看这家伙
Check out this guy.
那一只最烦人
Hey, that one is a pain in the ass.
特自以为是
Thinks he's special or something.
诡异
Freaky.
过来
Hey, come here.
他好像在思考什么似的
It's like he's thinking or something...
天哪  他掐住他的喉咙了
Oh, my God! He's got his throat!
放了他  快放了他
Let him go! Let go!
你没事吧  没事
Are you okay? I'm okay.
哥们  说了别靠得太近的
I told you not to get too close, man.
快点  伙计们  走吧
Come on, guys. Let's get out of here.
《凯撒传》
有些事是无法改变的
Some things aren't meant to be changed.
你得接受这个事实
You need to accept that.
你们在搞什么
Hey! What's going on here?
多试验一下113号  我们正准备
More 113 trials. We're just prepping...
不行  我们得先分析库巴的血液情况
No, we have to analyze Koba's blood work first.
富兰克林晓得程序  他人呢
Franklin knows this. Where is he?
他已经生病两天了
He's been out sick for two days.
我没有授权这么做
Well, I didn't authorize this.
你是没有
No.
我授权的
I did.
我们说好先只在一个受体上保守试验的
We agreed to test sparingly on one subject.
那个受体表现惊人
And that one subject is stunning.
这是一种病毒
It's a virus,
还不知道它对人体的影响
we don't know the human-related effects.
药有效  威尔  告诉他  琳达
The drug works, Will. Tell him, Linda.
作为新手  库巴在汉诺塔中拿到了满分
For starters, Koba scored a perfect 15 on the Lucas Tower.
每一次试验都验证了它的药效
Every test result verifies its effectiveness.
不能再试验了  你在说什么
No more tests. What are you...
直到我们弄清楚
Not until we have a better understanding
我们在做什么
of what we're dealing with.
我来告诉你我们在面对些什么
Look, I'll tell you exactly what we're...
等我们一会儿
Look. Just give us a minute.
有劳  请把大猩猩放回笼子  温柔点
Excuse me, put the ape back in the cage, and be gentle.
威尔  我来告诉你我们在做什么
Will, I'll tell you exactly what we're dealing with here.
我们在做一种
We're dealing with a drug
比我们所有其他的研究加起来
that is worth more than everything else
还要值钱的药
we are developing combined.
你创造历史  我赚大钱
You make history, I make money.
不正如你我所愿吗
Wasn't that our arrangement?
不行  风险太大
No, there are risks.
别跟我谈什么风险
Don't talk to me about risks.
你给自己的父亲用上了实验中的药物
You gave your own father an experimental drug.
我一个电话就可以结束你的职业生涯
I could finish your career with one phone call.
不用麻烦你了  我辞职
I'll save you the trouble. I quit.
没有你我们还是会继续
We will proceed without you.
听着  你不知道你在做什么
Look, you don't know what you're doing.
这些实验需要有遏制
These tests need to be contained.
你都不知道113号是否稳定
You have no idea if the 113 is stable,
会对人体带来怎样的伤害
what kind of damage it can do to people.
正是如此  我们才在猩猩上试验
Yes. Well, that is why we test it on chimps.
不是吗
Isn't it?
罗德曼博士  是我  富兰克林
Dr. Rodman, it's me, Franklin!
我有话对你说
I need to talk to you!
请为我开门
Can you come to the door?
博士
Doc?
你他妈是谁
Who the hell are you?
滚出去
Get out of here!
对不起  对不起
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
你不是想陷害我吧
You wouldn't be trying to entrap me, would you?
我不能说我同意了
Well, I can't say I approve.
它们又不是人
They're not people, you know.
你到底让不让他离开
You gonna let him go or not?
凯撒  嘿  过来
Caesar? Hey, come on.
来呀  我们回家
Come on, we're going home.
回家
Home.
过来  是真的
Come on, we're really going.
来  我们离开这儿
Come on. Let's get out of here.
过来
Come on.
凯撒?
Caesar?
大概他更喜欢和同类在一起
I guess he likes it better here with his own kind.
为什么给火箭饼干
Why cookie Rocket?
猩猩不团结
Apes alone...
力量太弱
weak.
团结在一起才强大
Apes together strong.
猿都蠢
Apes stupid.
该死的  罗德尼
Damn it, Rodney!
你又把水管留在天井里了吗
You leave the hose out in the atrium again?
什么  我没有
What? No!
快点  动起来
Come on! Let's go!
快点  起床了
Come on, get up!
点火升空八个月后
Eight months after its launch,
最新消息  伊卡洛斯号进入火星大气层
点火升空八个月后
Eight months after its launch,
最新消息  伊卡洛斯号进入火星大气层
地球第一座载人飞船到达火星
Earth's first manned space flight to Mars...
最新消息  伊卡洛斯号进入火星大气层
地球第一座载人飞船到达火星
Earth's first manned space flight to Mars...
我发誓  道奇  我说的是实话
I swear, Dodge, I'm telling the truth.
是吗  如果你没有偷我的饼干
Yeah, well, if you didn't take my cookies
那是谁他妈干的
then who the hell did?
我不知道
I don't know.
你们两个白痴有完没完
Will you two morons knock it off?
我要回家了
I'm going home.
猩猩屋里都比这安宁
I get more peace in the goddamn ape house.
爸  对不起
Dad, I'm sorry.
有你的啊  罗德尼  我发誓
Well done, Rodney. I swear...
富兰克林先生?  我是多蒂
Mr. Franklin? It's Dottie.
富兰克林先生?
Mr. Franklin?
有人吗
Hello?
搞什么飞机
What the hell?
神说  水是万物之源
God said, "Let the waters bring forth moving creatures..."
罗德尼  立刻到平台上来
Rodney, get to the platform now.
罗德尼
Rodney!
你他妈以为自己在干什么啊?
What the hell do you think you're doing, huh?
滚进去
Get!
进去  滚回你的笼子去
Go on. Get back in your cage.
我警告你
I'm warning you.
进去  进去
Go on, get!
好
That's it.
怎么样  你自讨苦吃  现在滚进去
See? That's what you get! Now get back!
你有毛病啊
What's wrong with you?
蠢猴子
Dumb monkey!
把你的臭爪子拿开  该死的臭狒狒
Take your stinking paw off me, you damn dirty ape!
不
No!
不  不  不
No! No! No!
不  不
No! No!
不
No!
我发誓我一定剥了你们每一个的皮
I swear I'm gonna skin each and every one of you!
基因系统公司
卡罗琳  你上去过凯撒的房间吗
Caroline, have you been up to Caesar's room?
没人听电话
No one is answering.
兰顿
Landon?
威尔
Will?
Will!
发生什么了
What happened?
他说话了
He spoke.
你说什么
What do you... what?
你的猩猩
Your ape.
讲话了
He spoke.
旧金山纪事报  迷失太空?
怎么会
What in the hell?
难以置信
I don't believe this.
我要剥了你们每一个的皮
...I'm gonna skin each and every one of you!
我需要有人与旧金山警察局协调一下
I need someone to coordinate with the SFPD.
告诉他们这边出了人命
Tell them we got a fatality.
怎么了?  我知道他要去哪
What is it? I know where he's headed.
伦
Len?
我们走
Let's go.
我是雅各布
Jacobs.
雅各布先生  我是威尔组里的琳达
Mr. Jacobs, it's Linda from Will's team.
发生了件可怕的事
Something horrible has happened.
富兰克林死了  死于病毒感染
Franklin is dead, from a viral infection.
你在说些什么
The hell are you talking about?
他曾暴露在113号病毒下
He was exposed to the 113.
它对人体的危害不作用于猩猩
It does something to people that it doesn't do to apes.
他会穿过旧金山  越过金门大桥
He'll have to go through the city and across the bridge.
雅各布先生?
Mr. Jacobs?
雅各布先生  你还在听吗...
Mr. Jacobs, are you...
搞什么鬼
What the hell?
我是史提芬•雅各布
Steven Jacobs!
这是我的公司  有人闯入了
This is my facility. We've had a breach.
我们需要空中支援
We need to get up in the air
找到他们  灭了他们  知道吗
and track them down and destroy them! Okay?
等等  等等
Wait a sec! Wait a second.
听着  这事你得相信我
Look. You've got to trust me on this! Okay?
大伙儿最好把照相机准备好
You guys might want to get your cameras ready.
这些家伙一般都比较害羞
Normally these guys are quite shy.
他们刚刚穿过北边的一个公园
They just tore through a park on the north side.
他们有领袖  按住通话键
They're being led! Got to hold the button!
什么  按住通话键
What? The button!
他们有领袖  他们比你想象的聪明得多
They're being led! These apes are smarter than you think!
我们得杀了领头的
We've got to kill the leader!
旧金山湾区动物关怀与控制署
不是  别跟他们说我被堵在路上了
No, you do not tell them I am stuck in traffic.
编个聪明点的理由  先别挂电话
You make up something smarter! Hold on.
搞什么
What the...
他们在桥上
They're on the bridge.
他们是要去红树林
They're trying to get to the redwoods.
旧金山警察局一号  我是空警队
SFPD Police One, this is Air Ops.
封锁桥南  骑警那边什么状况
Seal off the south end. What's the status of the mounted units?
准备就绪  长官
Good to go, sir.
很好
All right.
一等他们靠近你们  就把他们往北逼
As soon as they reach you, push north!
桥北
North side,
我们准备把他们逼向你们
we're going to push them right to you.
没问题  我们准备好了
No probIem, we're ready for them.
桥北已封锁
North side is locked.
绝不会让他们通过
They'll never get through here.
一等他们到达中间地带  就地消灭
As soon as they hit the gap, we'll take them out!
你们会开枪射杀吗
You're going to shoot them?
如同射杀瓮中之鳖
Like shooting fish in a barrel.
很好
Good.
转向转向  继续走  请下桥  先生
Turn that thing around. Keep moving. Get off this bridge, sir.
不  你不明白  你才不明白
No, you don't understand. You don't understand!
立刻下桥  这是疏散命令  下车
Get off this bridge now! This is an evacuation. Get out!
所有平民已撤离  请确认
All civilians clear. Please confirm.
把这些人赶下桥
Get these people off the bridge!
等等
Wait!
你们从上面走
Go up.
你们从桥下走
Get under.
让开道  骑警要来了
Stand by to send in mounted units.
他们要大开杀戒
They're gonna slaughter them.
我去找凯撒
I'm going to get Caesar.
听着
Listen.
小心点
You be careful.
下来  你不能上那儿去
Get down from there. You're not allowed up there.
可我要我的车  放开我
But I have to get to my car! Let go of me!
我得去车里  有很重要的事
I've got to get to my car. It's important!
把他们往北赶
Push them north!
让开
Get out of the way!
不要
No!
动作利索点  不然躲进雾里就看不见了
Quick or you'll lose them in the fog!
开枪
Do it!
他们在哪  我找不到他们
Where are they? I can't see them.
桥北加州高速巡警  你们看得见他们吗
CHP North, do you have a visual?
不  长官  看不见
No, sir. Negative.
拉下保险栓
Safeties off!
别开枪  别开枪
Hold your fire! Hold your fire!
后退  后退  所有人回撤
Get back! Get back! Everybody, pull back!
凯撒
Caesar!
他在那儿  他就是领袖
That's him. That's the leader.
255号  请回答  你在车里吗
255, come in! Are you there?
救救我
Help me.
抓住我的手
Take my hand.
来呀  来呀
Come on. Come on.
快点
Come on.
不要
No.
来呀
Come on.
是你
Not you.
不  不
No! No!
蠢猴子
Stupid monkey!
不  不
No! No!
凯撒
Caesar!
Caesar?
凯撒
Caesar.
对不起  都是我的错
I'm sorry. This is my fault.
你要住手  这样不对
This has to stop. This isn't the way.
你知道人类能干出什么事来
You know what they're capable of.
和我一起回家吧
Please come home.
跟我回家  我会保护你的
If you come home, I'll protect you.
凯撒已经到家了
Caesar is home.
好
Okay.
凯撒找到家了
Caesar is home.
走吧
Go.
一群不明物体在湾区造成了
An unknown group have caused a major disturbance
巨大骚动
here in the Bay Area,
包括市立动物园和金门大桥
including the City Zoo and the Golden Gate Bridge,
导致大面积财产损失与部分人员伤亡
causing widespread damage and some reported injuries.
目击者还报告说
Eyewitnesses have also reported
看到猩猩在市区流窜而过
seeing apes running through the city.